Guide to the Bert Cunningham Papers, 1927-1943
Duke University. University Archives
Bert Cunningham papers 1927-1943
Duke University. University Archives
Cunningham, Bert, 1883-1943
2.2 linear feet Extent: 250 Items
Bert Cunningham was a professor of Biology and Zoology at Trinity College and Duke University from 1916-1943. His collection includes the manuscript and illustrations for his book Introduction to Biology for the College Students, as well as professional correspondence.
UA.29.02.0142
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Bert Cunningham Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1948; 1960.
Biographical Note
Cunningham was born in McLean County, Illinois in 1883. He received his B.S. and M.S. from Illinois Wesleyan University in 1908 and 1909, respectively, his A.M. from Trinity College in 1916 and his Ph.D. from the University of Wisconsin in 1920. At Trinity College, he served as president of the Faculty Club and chairman of the schedule committee of the university. In 1911, he first came to Durham to chair the High School Science Department. He joined the Trinity College faculty as instructor of Biology in 1916, specializing in endocrinology, histology and heredity. His Axial Bifurcation in Serpents: An Historical Survey of Serpent Monsters Having Part of the Axial was published in 1937 by Duke University Press. Cunningham died in 1943, before his book Introduction to Biology for the College Students could be published.
Collection Overview
Collection contains correspondence relating to the Duke Department of Zoology, the N.C. Academy of Science, and the Phi Gamma Delta fraternity. Also includes a final revised typescript copy of Cunningham's Introduction to Biology for the College Students as well as correspondence relating to the possible publication of this book.
Subject Headings
Cunningham, Bert; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- History -- 20th century; Trinity College (Durham, N.C.) -- Faculty; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University. Dept. of Zoology; Zoology -- Study and teaching (Higher)
Related Material
Department of Zoology Records, 1905-1997.
University Archives, Duke University.
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004.
University Archives, Duke University.
Photograph Collection, 1861-2006.
University Archives, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Container List, 3 Boxes
  - Publishers' Correspondence, 1927-1941 (Box 1)
  - Publishers' Correspondence, 1927-1941 (Box 1)
  - Publishers' Correspondence, 1927-1941 (Box 1)
  - Publishers' Correspondence, 1927-1941 (Box 1)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Professional Correspondence, Duke Memos, 1929-1935 (Box 1)
  - 1943 Cunningham Memorial (Box 1)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Biology and Zoology Program Information, 1932-1934 (Box 1)
  - Animal Diagrams (Box 2)
  - Animal and Fish Internal Diagrams (Box 2)
  - Introduction to Biology for College Students Manuscript and Illustrations (Box 2)
  - Suggested Reading Lists (Box 2)
  - Biology Exams (Box 2)
  - Introduction to Biology for College Students, Diagrams: (Oversize-box 3)
    - Animal Diagrams (Oversize-box 3)
    - Plant Diagrams (Oversize-box 3)
    - Amoeba and Cell Diagrams (Oversize-box 3)
    - Snail Diagrams (Oversize-box 3)
    - Maps (Oversize-box 3)
    - Prints of People (Oversize-box 3)